Okay בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*.
Today's דף daf *Daf* is ט"ז *Tet-Zayin*. We pick up with the
משנה Mishna *Mishnah* at the bottom of ט"ו *Tet-Vav* עמוד ב' amud
bet, *Amud-Bet*. We dealt with a lot of very important conceptual issues
yesterday in the larger context of a תנאי tnai *Tenai* and a
נדר Neder, *Neder*. We dealt with the issue about first of all
not a נדר Neder. *Neder* issue directly at all but a very
important question about the husband's rights to have sex with his wife,
the wife's right to have sex with her husband, the way that
creates almost a sense of ownership of one on the other person's
person or body, and therefore the implications of that for a נדר
Neder, *Neder*.
And we also had the idea of the idea of בל יחל
*Bal Yachel*, a rabbinic בל יחל *Bal Yachel* on just an abstract
idea like walking etc. sleeping even if it's not specifically about a
physical part of the body. And also the idea of a בל
יחל *Bal Yachel* on a מנהג *Minhag* of treating certain things as
forbidden and to what degree that ties into a general idea of
a נדר Neder, *Neder* in terms of doing a מצווה mitzvah. *Mitzvah*
type of an act going back to the more biblical or related
to the biblical concept of נדר Neder. *Neder*, but also specifically about
making things forbidden, certain actions forbidden, which therefore does harken closer to
the type of נדר Neder, *Neder* we were talking about, you know,
about making the status of something forbidden and again here talking about
that thing as a type of an action. Okay so now the
גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* goes up with the following starts with the next
משנה Mishna *Mishnah*.
Oh excuse me and then a very very important point I just
want to review that came up in the ר"ן Ran *Ran* discussing
the position of רמב"ם *Rambam*, which is if one person makes something
forbidden against to another person and the other person eats it right
who gets lashes? So the ר"ן Ran *Ran* says it's always the
doer who gets lashes, the one who violates the vow. רמב"ם *Rambam*
says that the only person that would get lashes is the person
that both made the vow and violated it, which doesn't mean it's
permissible, you know, for somebody to violate if he or she did
not make it, but that that would not be the lashes in
the תורה Torah *Torah*. The lashes in the תורה Torah *Torah* is
לא יחל דברו lo yachel devaro. *Lo Yachel Devaro*. So the ר"ן
Ran *Ran* fully ignores this sort of act of, you know, fully
focuses I should say on the state of the object and once
that object is given that state anyone who violates it gets lashes.
רמב"ם *Rambam* does not necessarily deny that, but says that for but
to fully violate the biblical prohibition and to get lashes that would
require not just violating the state of the object but violating one's
own vow and therefore only done by the person him or herself.
Okay so a lot of very important issues yesterday and we'll deal
with also a lot of very related important issues today. So let's
take a look. שבועה שאיני ישן, Shvuah she'eini yashen, שאיני מדבר, she'eini
medaber, שאיני מהלך, she'eini mehalech, אסור assur. *Shevuah she'aini yashen, she'aini medaber,
she'aini mehalech, assur*. If somebody says a שבועה Shvuah. *Shevuah* that I
will not sleep, that I will not talk, that I will not
go with you, it is forbidden. Now that is similar to the
נדר neder. *Neder* in a way it's more obvious right cause this
is action
related and a person's taking a שבועה Shvuah *Shevuah* that he won't
do certain actions,
so that's very straightforward. The חידוש *Chiddush* really was the משנה Mishna
*Mishnah* yesterday, right if you remember the משנה Mishna *Mishnah* yesterday or
two days ago, קונם konam, שאני ישן, she'ani yashen, שאני מדבר, she'ani
medaber. שאני מהלך she'ani mahalech, *Konam she'ani yashen, she'ani medaber, she'ani mehalech*,
right in all those cases it is forbidden. Okay so the שבועה
Shvuah *Shevuah* is obvious that's the classic שבועה Shvuah *Shevuah* about an
action and it would be a biblical prohibition. The difference is a
נדר neder *Neder* is that we said that by a נדר neder
*Neder* it would be rabbinic if it's focused on the action and
not on an object. Also we had said that the language here
is אסור assur. *Assur* which presumably means biblically forbidden, by a נדר
neder *Neder* it said בל יחל דברו yakhel devaro? *Bal Yachel Devaro*
so again we said it would be a rabbinic violation. So this
משנה Mishna *Mishnah* about what you say by שבועה shevua. *Shevuah* is
the same ruling by a נדר neder *Neder* except as we clarified
because it's about an action and not an object by a נדר
neder, *Neder* it would only be rabbinic. Also which should be noted
is the difference of language. By a שבועה shevua *Shevuah* it's a
שבועה shevua שאיני she'eini. ישן *Shevuah she'aini yashen* about the not, I
will not eat etc. By a נדר neder *Neder* it is שבועה
shevua שאני she'ani ישן *Shevuah she'ani yashen* meaning that what you are
doing is you are making the sleeping forbidden, the walking forbidden and
you are talking not in the negative but in the positive. Okay
so that's the first line of this משנה Mishna. *Mishnah* parallel to
a נדר neder, *Neder* except by a נדר neder *Neder* it is
presumably rabbinic, number one, and number two here it is the more
simply stated in the negative. I will not go as opposed to
my going is forbidden which would be the נדר neder, *Neder* version.
Next point. קרבן לא אוכל לך, Korban lo ochal lach, הקרבן שאוכל
לך Hakorban she-ochal lach. *Korban lo ochel lecha, ha-korban she-ochel lecha*. Now
we're going to start again with talking about a נדר neder *Neder*.
Okay so I'm just trying to make you appreciate the structure of
the משנה Mishna, *Mishnah*. Talked about walking, going, sleeping, נדר neder *Neder*,
שבועה shevua *Shevuah*, both of them you can make it but you
articulate it in different ways. Now we're talking about going to contrast
a נדר neder *Neder* to a שבועה shevua *Shevuah* about the classic
issue about eating something. So let's take a look. קרבן לא אוכל
לך, Korban lo ochal lach, הקרבן שאוכל לך Hakorban she-ochal lach, *Korban
lo ochel lecha, ha-korban she-ochel lecha*, lo ochel. לא קרבן לא אוכל
לך מותר. lo korban lo ochal lach mutar. Any of those articulations,
it is not a binding נדר, neder because if somebody just says
קרבן שאוכל לך, Korban she-ochal lach, that would be a binding נדר.
neder That which I would eat of yours or that loaf of
bread regarding its eating is a קרבן korban to me. That's a
classic נדר, neder, קרבן שאוכל לך. Korban she-ochal lach. So why are
these don't work? Because let's take a look. קרבן לא אוכל לך,
Korban lo ochal lach. well, that's obvious because again, ironically, by a
נדר, neder. if you frame it in the negative, you are, it's
not binding, right? You could say I won't do this, but that's
not a נדר. neder. You're saying נדר, neder that קרבן korban is
the eating of that loaf of bread. So if you say קרבן
לא אוכל לך, Korban lo ochal lach, so what does that mean?
A קרבן korban is the non-eating of that loaf of bread? So
that doesn't mean anything. The most it could mean is somebody's trying
to take a שבועה. shevua In the name of a קרבן, korban,
I won't eat you, but that's not לשון שבועה. Lashon shvuah. You
can't take a שבועה shevua in the name of a קרבן. korban.
Okay, so that's not binding. That's קרבן לא אוכל לך. korban lo
okhel lakh קרבן שאוכל לך, Korban she-ochal lach, now that seems like
it, well, if you say that seems like it should work, right?
קרבן שאוכל לך. Korban she-ochal lach. All right, so that would seem
like a, oh, so that would work. But you said הקרבן שאוכל
Hakorban she'ochal, לך. And you might remember earlier, if you said it
as one word, I don't know how we're supposed to know the
difference, but if you said הקרבן hakorban שאוכל she-ocheil לך, the קרבן
korban that I would eat of yours, that I will eat of
yours, that does work. That loaf of bread that regarding its eating
or whatever is a קרבן, korban, the קרבן, korban, whatever, that's classic
לשון נדר. Lashon neder. But ה, ha, pause, קרבן שאוכל לך Korban
she-ochal lach is seen as like לשון שבועה. Lashon shvuah. In the
name of a קרבן, korban, ה, ha, behold, קרבן שאוכל לך. Korban
she-ochal lach. Or in the name of a
קרבן, korban, I will eat from your things or something of that
nature, it seems הקרבן hakorban, makes it sound like you're making a,
what's that called? Not a, not an expletive,
an exclamation. But there's a word for that, like you say,
behold or there's an ex... not exhortation. I can't think of the
word. Anyway, so nobody else can, so I don't feel that stupid.
Okay, anyway, but behold! By a קרבן, korban, I will eat you!
So the ה ha makes it less about describing the state and
more about an action and again therefore makes it לשון שבועה. Lashon
shvuah. And then presumably you're also not bound by a שבועה shevua
to eat it because you don't take a שבועה shevua. in the
name of a קרבן. korban. Okay, so the middle one was the
one most likely could have worked, but it was because of the
pause between the ה ha and the קרבן korban that it means
something else. לא קרבן לא אוכל לך. Lo korban lo ochal lach.
It is not a קרבן korban that which I would not eat,
will not eat, right? So there מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן. miklal
lav atah shomeia hen. You could say if it's not a קרבן
korban that which I will not eat of yours, then that which
I will eat of yours is a קרבן. korban. Okay, so that
should work. Except that we've been saying that our משנה Mishna assumes
like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, you don't say מכלל לאו אתה שומע
הן. miklal lav atah shomeia hen. And this is a classic מכלל
לאו אתה שומע הן. miklal lav atah shomeia hen. It's not what
you... that thing of yours
is a non-חולין, chulin, which might mean it's a קרבן. korban. Here
it is not a קרבן korban that which I will not eat,
which could reasonably mean that which I will eat is a קרבן,
korban, but not necessarily. And therefore that's not binding. Okay, so the
first and the last one are pretty obvious, the middle one is
because of the pause between the words ה ha and קרבן. korban.
Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara מני מתניתין? Mani matnisin?
Who's our משנה Mishna going like? רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir here, it's
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. די רבי יהודה לא שני ליה קרבן ולא
שני ליה
הקרבן.
Di Rabbi Yehuda lo
shani lei korban velo shani lei hakorban. It wouldn't matter if you
said קרבן korban or הקרבן, meaning that the משנה mishna says, it
sounds like in the משנה mishna because you said קרבן לא אוכל
Korban lo ochal, לך, right, it doesn't work. It sounds like if
you would have said קרבן אוכל לך, Korban ochal lach, it would
have worked. But we know for רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, that's not
true. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda remember needs the כ. ke. כקרבן לא
אוכל לך. Ke-korban lo ochal lach. Right, so this משנה mishna seems
to feel that the prefixes don't really matter and that is not
רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda position. Okay, אימא סיפא, eima seifa, let's look
at the end of the משנה. mishna. לקרבן li-korban or לא קרבן
לא אוכל לך lo korban lo ochal lach, מותר. mutar. והתנן לקרבן
לא אוכל לך רבי מאיר אוסר. Ve-hatnan li-korban lo ochal lach Rabbi
Meir oser.
When you say לקרבן לא אוכל לך, li-korban lo ochal lach, even
though you say the לא, lo, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says it's
forbidden. ואמר רבי אבא נעשה כאומר לקרבן יהא, Ve-amar Rabbi Abba na'aseh
k'omer li-korban yehei,
you put a period in the sentence. It should be a קרבן,
korban, period. רפיסא ולא אוכל לך, Refisah velo ochal lach, therefore I
won't eat you. So how come in the last case of the
משנה, Mishnah, when we said לא קרבן לא אוכל לך, lo korban
lo okhel lakh why don't we translate it as לקרבן, li-korban, period,
לא אוכל לך? lo ochal lach? And the answer's obvious because the
end of the משנה Mishnah didn't say לקרבן, li-korban, it said לא
קרבן. lo korban. So the גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא. lo kashya.
הא דאמר לקרבן, ha d'amar li-korban, if you say it should be
for a קרבן, korban, then we'll put a period and then we'll
say it should be for a קרבן, korban, period, לא אוכל, lo
ochal, therefore I won't eat you. That would work. הא דאמר לא
לקרבן. ha d'amar lo li-korban. The end of the משנה Mishnah, you
said actually לא, lo, it is not a קרבן, korban, and therefore
we would have to reverse it to say it is a קרבן
korban that which I will eat. לא לקרבן דלא הא... lo li-korban
delo ha... דלא הוי d'la havei קרבן korban קאמר, ka'amar, you're saying
it's not a קרבן. korban. Okay. So we keep on sort of
rehashing some of these discussions from before, again, maybe the משנה Mishnah
doesn't require a כי, ki, that's not what's significant in the משנה
Mishnah so it's רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, the end of the משנה
Mishnah is also consistent with רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, you don't say
מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן, miklal lav ata shomea hen, just because
it's not a קרבן korban that which I don't eat, doesn't mean
it is a קרבן korban that which I will eat. And we
just reconciled it with the one unusual statement of רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir, לקרבן לא אוכל לך lekorban lo ochel lecha works, that's because
you put a period. לקרבן, lekorban, period, therefore לא אוכל לך, lo
ochel lecha, but that only worked if you said לקרבן lekorban and
that's not the case here in the
משנה.
Mishnah Okay.
Interjection. Thank you. That's the word I was looking for. It's an
interjection. Okay. So.
Did you mean to interject? I know.
It's funny, what are you interjecting in? You could be starting a
sentence with an interjection. But yes, that's the word I was looking
for. Okay, moving on. All right, so fine. So the most interesting
thing about that was really something we had seen before, which is
הקרבן אוכל לך, ha'korban ochel lecha, that if you said קרבן אוכל
לך korban ochel lecha it would work, but by adding the word
ה, ha, you sort of turned it into a שבועה. shevua. Okay
now, those נדרים nedarim that don't work are now going to be
contrasted to שבועות shevuos which do work. So let's take a look.
In the exact same formulation. שבועה לא אוכל לך, shevua lo ochel
lecha, a שבועה shevua that I won't eat your stuff, okay, השבועה
שאוכל לך, ha'shevua she'ochel lecha, or behold the שבועה shevua of that
of your stuff which I will eat, I'll get back to the
מילתיה, milteih, or לא שבועה לא אוכל לך lo shevua lo ochel
lecha אסור. assur Or a not שבועה shevua that I won't eat
of yours is forbidden. Okay, so this is exactly the same language
we had before by נדר. neder By נדר neder, it's מותר, mutar,
by שבועה shevua, it's אסור. assur. Everybody sees that it's exactly the
same, right?
So as opposed to שאני she'ani מהלך, שאני ישן, שאני אוכל, she'ani
ochel, right, which we had before where we said that נדר neder
and שבועה shevua, was basically the same, except by a שבועה shevua
you had to say שאני and by I mean by a נדר
neder you had to say שאני and by a שבועה shevua you
had to say שאיני. Okay, remember? But when we talked about sleeping
or walking or so on, there they both were binding.
Here there's a difference. By the נדר neder. when you say it
in this language it's not binding, by a שבועה shevua when you
say it in this language it is binding. Now let's figure out
why this all works by a שבועה. shevu'ah So the first case
is obvious. שבועה לא אוכל לך, shevua lo ochel lecha, that's a
classic שבועה. shevu'ah שבועה shevu'ah, I won't eat, so you don't eat.
The last case is problematic. I'm going to get back to the
middle cause it's the most difficult. The last case is problematic because
that's
a מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן. miklal lav ata shomea hen. A
not שבועה shevu'ah that I won't eat of yours. Which has to
then be reversed to a שבועה shevu'ah of what I will eat
of yours, right? So don't you say מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן
miklal lav ata shomea hen according to this? So I don't know
if there are other answers, but all the ראשונים rishonim on the
דף basically point to a גמרא Gemara in שבועות Shevuos that say
that even רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says, you know the category that
you don't say מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן miklal lav ata shomea
hen is based on the תנאי of בני גד ובני ראובן Bnei
Gad u'Bnei Reuven of crossing over the ירדן Yarden and, you know,
getting an inheritance in the land of כנען. Canaan. That it wasn't
just enough to say if you cross over you'll get, you had
to say if you don't cross over you won't get. So the
גמרא Gemara says that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir only requires both like
sort of being fully explicit in something that relates to ממון. mammon.
That relates to property. Or you know so therefore, by a נדר,
neder a נדר neder relates to objects. So somehow, again, I cannot
explain this logically, this becomes just a formal, you know, parameter. That
when it relates to ownership, property, objects, that's when you have to
say things in both directions. When it's just a שבועה, shevu'ah. then
you don't have to say things in both directions, you know, then
it's enough to say one and imply the other. I mean, I
suppose to the degree you wanted to give a סברא sevara for
this, you would say that, you know, things that relate to property
and objects affect other people. So it's a little bit like the
principle about דברים שבלב אינם דברים. dvarim she'balev einam dvarim. That you
can't have something in your mind you have to make it explicit,
but that is a requirement primarily when you're dealing with two-sided interactions
when there are other people involved. When it's just between you and
God, you know, or it's unilateral, you know, more it could be
more relevant what you're thinking. So here too, if it's a נדר,
neder although I could make a נדר neder. of something forbidden on
me and not involve anybody else, but once it's about physical objects
in the real world, you know, a lot of cases could involve
other people and therefore maybe it requires to be fully explicit. So
you can't just say one and imply the reverse. Okay, whereas by
a שבועה, shevu'ah a שבועה shevu'ah is really just a an obligation
I take upon myself and it's between me and God and there's
no ממון mammon involved as it were, and therefore you can imply
you can apply imply the reverse.
As far as God there's no difference between your thought and your
articulation.
Oh that's not true, a
שבועה shevu'ah God knows everything,
that is true, but a שבועה shevu'ah still requires דיבור, dibbur, meaning
there's all yeah, so that but that has to do also like
וידוי viduy requires דיבור, dibbur, like how much do you make something
real to yourself, you know. even if there's no other person involved,
okay, about articulating it. דאווענינג, Davening, right? There's a ט״ז Taz that
wants to know that since דאווענינג davening is עבודה שבלב, avodah she-be-lev,
maybe you don't have to say the words. But you know, but
all of the evidence is that you do have to say the
words and the simplest explanation is because even though God knows to
a certain degree you don't know fully until you explicate it. It
doesn't have the same power. Okay, but back to the משנה, Mishna
the problem still in the משנה Mishna. is the middle case which
also really relates to the last case, which is why is שבועה
שאוכל לך shevu'ah she-ocheil l'cha forbidding? I mean if why don't we
just translate it as now you've obligated yourself to eat it? How
do we translate that as now you're forbidden to eat it? So
we'll see in the גמרא Gemara but basically the translation we will
give the words is, let me violate a שבועה shevu'ah? if I
eat any of your things. Okay? So we translate it in the
negative. So why should we translate it in the negative? Why don't
we take the guy at his word that he's taking a שבועה
shevu'ah is that he should eat? Okay, but we'll see that, but
the גמרא Gemara. will explain that as a particular context where שאוכל
she-ocheil means a שבועה, shevu'ah I you know, you know, should I
like, like, you know, I should violate a שבועה shevu'ah let me
be bound by a שבועה shevu'ah or you know that I what
you know if I were to eat anything of yours. So therefore
the שאוכל she-ocheil is more like the if, not what I will
do. If I were to eat your things, I will have violated
a שבועה. shevu'ah Okay and that's the middle case and that's why
it's forbidden. And in a way that's also the last case, right?
לא שבועה לא אוכל לך. lo shevu'ah lo ocheil l'cha. If you
real, if you really did reverse it, it would be שבועה אוכל
לך. shevu'ah ocheil l'cha. So again why doesn't that obligate you to
eat? Why does it obligate you to not eat? So ironically in
this משנה, Mishna the אוכל ocheil becomes means לא אוכל lo ocheil
and we'll have to see why in the גמרא. Gemara. So let's
take a look in the גמרא. Gemara Yes?
I mean it seems like such a simple question but does a
שבועה shevu'ah ever compel you to do something? Sure! Yeah! It's equal,
right? It's not just for forbidding.
Exactly and that's exactly what the גמרא's Gemara. going to ask. Since
a שבועה shvua can obligate you to, why do we read the
cases in the משנה Mishna of שאוכל she-ocheil to mean שלא אוכל?
she-lo ocheil? So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara מכלל,
mich'lal, this משנה Mishna implies דהא de-ha שבועה שאוכל לך shevu'ah she-ocheil
l'cha דלא אכילנא
משמע. de-lo achilna mashma. You gotta love it. A שבועה shevua, that
I will eat means I won't eat! Okay, but you know, anyway,
you can understand how sometimes people talk that way, right? Oh would
you mind if I joined the conversation? Sure! Yes, fine! So we
really mean no I don't mind but you say yes.
So sometimes people say the reverse of what they mean, yes?
Well throughout ש״ס Shas we have examples of them using euphemisms to
mean...
Well that's true but that's a euphemism, but that's true. Anyway, so
שאוכל she-ocheil means you know let me violate a שבועה shevua were
I to eat of yours, okay? לא אכילנא משמע. lo achilna mashma.
רמינהי? remini he? Is that really how you translate a positively phrased
שבועה? shevua We taught in a משנה Mishna in שבועות: Shavuot: שבועות
שתים שהן ארבע. shevu'ot shtayim she-hein arba. There are two categories of
שבועה shevua which break down into four, meaning the two are past
and future and the four are positive and negative of past and
positive and negative of future. What are they? שאוכל
ושלא אוכל, she-ocheil ve-she-lo ocheil, the future are I will eat or
I won't eat. שאכלתי ושלא אכלתי, she-achalti ve-she-lo achalti, I did eat
and I didn't eat. So clearly when you say שאוכל she-ocheil you
mean something different than when you say שלא אוכל, she-lo ocheil, okay?
A שבועה shevua does not only have to be as Dov said
prohibitory, it could also obligate you to do something. מדקאמר mide-ka'amar שלא
אוכל she-lo ocheil או o שאוכל ושלא אוכל she-ocheil ve-she-lo ocheil שאכלתי
ושלא אכלתי she-achalti ve-she-lo achalti מכלל mich'lal דשאוכל לך de-she-ocheil l'cha דאכילנא
משמע. de-achilna mashma. When you say that I will eat it means
I will eat, that you're obligating yourself to eat, not to not
eat. אמר אביי, amar Abaye, so basically how do you explain that
the case in our משנה Mishna. שאוכל she-ocheil means I won't eat?
שאוכל she-ocheil שתי לשונות משמע. shtei leshonot mashma. It could mean it
has two meanings. היו מסרבים בו לאכול, hayu mesarvim bo le'echol, if
they were trying to sort of force him to eat, you know
saying No no no I'm on a diet and they say Please
please eat eat! So then ואמר ve-amar אכילנא אכילנא. achilna achilna. He
says Yes fine fine I'll eat and so שבועה שאוכל. shevu'ah she-ocheil.
And fine I take an oath I will eat, leave me alone,
I promise you I'll eat, eat, okay שבועה שאוכל, shevu'ah she-ocheil, okay
there's gotta be a Jewish mother joke in here somewhere. Anyway, דאכילנא
משמע. de-achilna mashma. That means I will eat. Alright, אבל aval אמר,
amar, but if he
said לא אכילנא לא אכילנא, lo achilna lo achilna, stop I'm not
eating I'm not eating, והדר אמר ve-hadar amar שבועה שאוכל, shevu'ah she-ocheil,
a שבועה shevua that I should eat! Okay, notice how he said
that I should eat, right? That's sort of the difference. A שבועה
shevua that I will eat or that I should eat! שבועה דאוכל,
shevu'ah d'ocheil, so if he would say No no I'm not going
to eat, a שבועה shevua that I should eat! Okay, that
means דלא אכילנא קאמר. de-lo achilna ka'amar. That it means I won't
eat. It's I should violate a שבועה shvuah, should I eat from
this! Okay? So it all depends on context. Now what's the default
context? So obviously the גמרא Gemara in שבועות Shavuot makes it clearer
that the default context if you say שאוכל she'ocheil means you will
eat, even if there's no context in a vacuum we take the
words literally: you will eat. But in a particular context... say a
שבועה שאוכל shvua she'ocheil means actually I should violate a שבועה shvuah
were I to eat and that actually means that you won't eat.
Okay,
so where were we?
Okay, so he says like this: רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar,
רב אשי Rav Ashi says, שאוכל דשבועה שאי אוכל קאמר. she'ocheil d'shvua
she'ei ocheil ka'amar.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, no, no, שבועה שאוכל shvua she'ocheil
only means I will eat. In the משנה Mishna however, apparently what
he's doing is he's rereading the language of the משנה. mishna When
the משנה mishna? says שבועה שאוכל, shvua she'ocheil,
it really is saying שבועה שאי אוכל. shvua she'ei ocheil. If you
stretch out the אלף, alef, שאי אוכל, she'ei ocheil, I don't know.
Anyway, so the משנה mishna. really means שאי אוכל, she'ei ocheil, but
if you just said שאוכל she'ocheil it would mean eat. Okay. אם
כן, im kein, the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא מאי למימרא, pshita mai
l'meimra, if that's what the משנה mishna, is saying that you literally
say שאי אוכל, she'ei ocheil, that's obvious. No. מהו דתימא מיקם לישנא
הוא דאיתקלה, mahu d'teima meikam lishna hu d'itkala,
maybe even if he said שאי אוכל, she'ei ocheil, maybe he just
like slipped up articulating and he really wants to say שאוכל she'ocheil,
because as the ראשונים Rishonim say it's not a normal way to
talk שאי אוכל. she'ei ocheil. A person would say שלא אוכל shelo
ocheil or שאינני אוכל she'einani ocheil or something like that. So שאי
אוכל she'ei ocheil would be a funny way of saying it. So
even if that's what he said, we should interpret it to mean
שאוכל, she'ocheil, קא משמע לן ka mashma lan that we don't interpret
it that way. Okay, but bottom line is that the משנה mishna
is you did not say שאוכל, she'ocheil you said שאי אוכל. she'ei
ocheil. Okay. Yes.
Yeah, I just think this is really, this is really interesting because
you can't easily reflect orthographically how the language
sounds, trying to capture what it sounds like. You've got two אלפין
alefin in front of each other: אלף, alef, יוד, yud, אלף, alef,
ואו, vov, כף, chof, למד. lamed.
Right, right, right.
What does that sound like? Exactly, exactly. In the fourth century in
בבל. Bavel.
Exactly, exactly.
It's really interesting. Was אלף alef always silent?
Yeah, עין ayin was guttural, I don't know.
Yeah, it has to do with a pause, like he said, it's
the slight pause, the air flow.
If this is the way we communicate with each other, how do
we, is it very possible that trying to create contracts with non-Jews
and we're thinking this way, that this sounds like this but it
doesn't mean it, it means the opposite? Are we actually doing contracts
like this with non-Jews?
No, so that's true. Meaning that's the, you know, gets to that
this is all very much about a נדר, neder.
which is, again, you start...
no, I mean, no what you're asking is, I mean I don't
know why specifically you're asking the non-Jew case, but it is a
question, I mean maybe because it's harder for them to, you know,
how do you sort of bridge the gap of different languages or
of different, you know, cultures. But I mean, I think the similar
question could be asked even between two Jews, right? Which is how
much if you were talking about a contract would you sort of
as much look into all this type of context and use it
to say the exact reverse of what the words are actually written.
I think that this is, A, it's not written. You know, if
it's written maybe I think that that puts you more into somehow
some objective rather than contextual meaning of the words. But B, you
could imagine a non-written contract that I sold you something and I
said what I was selling you and then we did a transaction
and we didn't write it down, right? It's a good question. Like
would you use context as much in a monetary two-sided transaction, right,
as you do here in a נדר neder which although I mentioned
a more of a two-sided element, it's still fundamentally a ritual type
of a thing and not a... so that's a good question. That's
a really good question, how much would you use context like this
in other cases. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says אביי לא אמר
טעם כרב אשי. Abaye lo amar ta'am k'Rav Ashi. So
אביי Abaye didn't say like רב אשי. Rav Ashi. I mean, again,
the language here is different than in the rest of the מסכתות.
masechtos. Rest of the מסכתות masechtos it would say אביי לא אמר
כרב אשי. Abaye lo amar k'Rav Ashi. Why but here it's saying
לא אמר טעם כרב אשי. lo amar ta'am k'Rav Ashi. אביי Abaye
did not say the approach of רב אשי Rav Ashi who basically
saying switch the text to say שאי אוכל. she'ei ocheil. Okay, so
he didn't like רב אשי'ס Rav Ashi's approach
דלא קתני שאי אוכל d'lo katani she'ei ocheil because רב אשי Rav
Ashi switched the גרסא girsa of the משנה. mishna The משנה mishna.
says שאוכל she'ocheil and רב אשי Rav Ashi to make it say
the negative switched it to say שאי אוכל. she'ei ocheil. Okay, so
that's why he didn't like רב אשי'ס Rav Ashi's approach. רב אשי
נדי מן טעם דאביי, Rav Ashi nadi min ta'am d'Abaye, again, very
strange language you would never have it in the rest of ש"ס.
Shas. The rest of ש"ס Shas it would be רב אשי לא
אמר כאביי. Rav Ashi lo amar k'Abaye. But נדי nadi means he
distanced himself from the approach of אביי, Abaye, right? So רב אשי
Rav Ashi didn't say like אביי, Abaye, he distanced himself from that
approach. קסבר, kasavar, why not, why not say that שאוכל she'ocheil depends
on context? Because he says if שאוכל depends on context then also
שלא אוכל shelo ocheil depends on context and everything depends on context,
nothing means anything. Okay, שלא אוכל נמי משמע שתי לשונות. shelo ocheil
nami mashma shtei lishonot. So if somebody also said I won't eat,
it could mean two opposite things. Why do we only give the
example that you say if you will eat it means not? You
should have said if you say I won't eat it means I
will. Okay, how could saying I won't eat mean I will? You
know.
Now again, this is very strange because it's the way the ראשונים
Rishonim the whole question about the גרסא girsa here, okay, but he
says but they explain this as rhetorical, which is funny, but why
it's giving this example. Eat, eat, he says, should I not eat?
Should I not eat? ואמר נמי שבועה, va'amar nami shevua, and an
oath, בין שאוכל בין שלא אוכל, bein she'okhel bein shelo okhel, whether
he says an oath that I will eat or an oath that
I won't eat, הדין אכילנא משמע, hadain achilna mashma, it means I
will eat. I don't exactly get it, but basically they say eat,
eat, and the person's saying rhetorically, you know, what I not eat?
You know, should I not eat? You know, and then שבועה, shvuah
should I not eat? Again, שבועה shvuah, should I not eat? That
that I won't eat, okay, so which is interpreted as that I
should transgress a שבועה shvuah were I not to eat this thing.
So in a particular context not would mean I would. Okay. ואמר
נמי שבועה בין שאוכל בין שלא אוכל הדין אכילנא משמע דאמר. va'amar
nami shevua bein she'okhel bein shelo okhel hadain achilna mashma de'amar. ואיכא
לתירוצי נמי לישנא דשבועה שלא אוכל ve'ika letirutzai nami lishna de'shevua shelo
okhel דלא אכילנא קאמר. dilo achilna ka'amar.
Or you could have said that under some circumstances I won't eat
means I won't eat. Okay. So basically if I will eat can
mean I won't, and I won't under the right circumstances can mean
I will. Okay. And therefore so אלא תנא פסיקא אפסקא, ela tana
psika apska, שאוכל אכילה משמע, she'okhel akhila mashma, שלא אוכל לא אכילה
משמע, shelo okhel lo akhila mashma, our
תנא tana is not paying attention to context. Either he's saying the
context wouldn't matter, we always just go by what you say and
we ignore context, or our תנא tana is going to tell you
what the default meaning is. Once we're going to say, oh well,
it all depends on the context, then how can we teach you
any rules? Because we'll all say, well, it all depends on the
context. So therefore it's a very reasonable point, right? A משנה Mishnah.
that says שבועה שאוכל shevua she'okhel and you say, well, it means
שלא אוכל shelo okhel because it describes you a very particular context.
How how's I supposed to know that from the משנה? Mishnah That
would not be פשט pshat in the משנה. Mishnah Okay. Anyway very
interesting here how at least according to אביי Abaye context could reverse
the meaning of something.
And אביי Abaye raises an important question about what would you say
about like transactions and context. I should also say two other brief
points before we get to the next משנה, Mishnah, which is
one is the point that Saul Lieberman made and the article I
mentioned the other day and sent out, which is you know you
could read this גמרא Gemara as it's all sort of like the
גמרא Gemara is just trying to deal with a difficult משנה Mishna
so it's creating this particular context of somebody saying eat eat and
him saying a שבועה shvuah I will or a שבועה shvuah, I
won't, but you have to sort of realize look I mean so
many of the משניות mishnayos are exactly this about I won't eat
this loaf of bread I will eat I won't eat, right? And
therefore what he basically he takes the גמרא Gemara at the face
value and he says like it just shows you how prolific and
loose I should say sloppy you know people were with making נדרים
ושבועות nedarim u'shevuos all the time. You go to somebody's you go
to somebody's meal and they say eat eat, no נדר neder I
won't eat, no שבועה shvuah, I won't, נדר neder that's אסור assur
to me, I'm on a diet, נדר neder the dessert you know
whatever so it's like you know that it sounds like right that
was just and that he says is part of what חז"ל Hazal
had to deal with is to try to rein that in and
put limits and say not all these things work there's particular formulas
you know to try to sort of do something about the whole
phenomenon. Yes Charlie.
It's relatively rare to have people taking a נדר neder or שבועה
shvuah, today. Right.
And by the opinion that we really shouldn't be doing this, this
would seem to contradict the principle of ירידת הדורות. yeridas hadoros.
All right that's a good point. I'm not sure ירידת הדורות yeridas
hadoros always relates to the issue of lay observance. ירידת הדורות yeridas
hadoros tends to relate to the intellectual religious level of the you
know elite. But yeah anyway but sometimes the ראשונים Rishonim do say
about ירידת הדורות yeridas hadoros in terms of lay observance that they
weren't frum enough to keep this in the time of the גמרא
Gemara how could we say anything anyway. All right the other point
I want to make is that תוספות Tosafos has a nice read
of the last clause of the משנה Mishna, לא שבועה לא אוכל
לך lo shevua lo okhel lakh which we said is bizarre because
even if you reverse it you're left with שבועה שאוכל shevua she'okhel
right? And he actually says the reason לא שבועה לא אוכל לך
lo shevua lo okhel lakh is binding is really a rabbinic גזירה
gezeira because you could accidentally drop off the word לא. lo. So
if you said instead of saying לא שבועה לא אוכל לך lo
shevua lo okhel lakh and you dropped off the first word לא
lo you'd wind up saying שבועה שלא אוכל. shevua shelo okhel. So
we have to translate it in that stricter way because it could
you could wind up saying that. Whereas לא נדר לא קרבן לא
אוכל לך lo neder lo korban lo okhel lakh where לא קרבן
לא אוכל לך lo korban lo ochal lach would not if you
said קרבן korban לא lo אוכל לך wouldn't be binding either. So
therefore by the קרבן korban, whether you said the לא lo. or
not it wouldn't be binding but by the שבועה shvuah it would
that's how he explains the last clause of the משנה.
Yes. Just a point back though in those days there were no
such things as hearing aids and people got older and it's so
easy to mis-think
that someone was
saying something and not hearing the לא.
Right that's a very interesting point. That was just that low. And
think the person said this and really said that.
That's a very interesting point. That's a that's a very
interesting point.
Excellent point. Yeah, no, you're right.
You get older not to hear something.
Right, yeah. Anyway, I couldn't tell you you were speaking too low.
Okay, moving on. Lou is interjecting.
All right, exactly. Next משנה. זה חומר בשבועות מנדרים. Zeh chomer b'shvuot
mib'nedarim.
So what we just have done is contrasted a series of statements
that if you said it as a נדר, neder right, it did
not work. קרבן korban, לא אוכל, הקרבן שאוכל, and if you said
it as a שבועה, shvuah it did work. So there are cases
that a שבועה shvuah is stricter than a נדר. neder, Again, because
most of these have to do with actions
and or whatever, but the particular formulations and it works by a
שבועה shvuah and not by a נדר. neder וחומר בנדרים משבועות, V'chomer
b'nedarim mib'shvuot, now the following way a נדר neder is stricter than
a שבועה, shvuah and this is an idea we've been discussing,
and now the גמרא Gemara, gets... משנה gets to it directly. כיצד?
Keitzad? אמר קונם סוכה שאני עושה, Amar konam sukkah she'ani oseh, לולב
שאני נוטל, lulav she'ani notel, תפילין שאני מניח. tfillin she'ani maniach.
This סוכה sukkah is forbidden on me, you know,
regarding my taking of it, or you know, wearing of it, or
the לולב lulav my taking, or the סוכה sukkah my sitting in
it, you know, my sitting in the סוכה sukkah is קרבן, korban,
is forbidden. That בנדרים אסור, b'nedarim assur, by a נדר neder it
works, cause I didn't directly contradict my obligation to sit in a
סוכה, sukkah, I just spoke about the status of the object. And
then when it comes time to sit in a סוכה, sukkah, then
I won't be able to because it's forbidden to me. בשבועות מותר,
Bishvuot mutar, but by a שבועה shvuah it's מותר. mutar. I'm not
forbidden to sit in a סוכה, sukkah, שאין נשבעין לעבור על המצוות.
she'ein nishba'in la'avor al hamitzvot. I can't obligate myself directly against my
pre-existing obligation, right? I can't make a שבועה shvuah to go against
what the תורה Torah, obligates me to do. But by a נדר,
neder I did not go against what the תורה Torah said, I
just turned all the סוכות sukkot into forbidden objects. And then when
it comes time to sit in the סוכה, sukkah, I am not
able to do it, but I didn't directly contradict it. Now, by
a שבועה, shvuah if you take the שבועה, shvuah it's not binding
and you go ahead and you sit in a סוכה sukkah or
you put on תפילין. tfillin. However, you are still going to give
you lashes for having made a שבועת שוא. shvuat shav. Okay, when
you took the שבועה, shvuah you took a שבועה shvuah that was
not binding, that was not able to take effect, and that was
contradicting your obligation, and therefore it was a שבועה shvuah in vain.
So you still transgress taking a שבועה shvuah in vain, but now
the שבועה shvuah. does not... is not binding on you and you
can go ahead and do the action. Yes.
And that's a biblical prohibition.
Exactly, well, that's why I said lashes. Okay, so now let's take
a look at the גמרא, Gemara דף טז עמוד ב. daph tet-zayin
amud bet.
חומר, Chomer, when it says the first part, you know, a שבועה
shvuah is more strict than a נדר neder because of these cases
about לא שבועה לא אוכל לך. lo shvuah lo ochal lach. מכלל
דנדר הוא? Mikhlal d'neder hu? It sounds like it's stricter than a
נדר neder in those cases, but to some degree it would still
be some type of a נדר. neder. והמותר קתני. Vehamutar ktani. The
משנה said like things like לא קרבן korban, לא אוכל לך as
opposed to לא שבועה לא אוכל לך, lo shvuah lo ochal lach,
by a נדר neder. it said it was completely
permissible. So it shouldn't say that a שבועה shvuah is stricter, it
should have, you know, it sounds like a נדר neder? still has
some binding in that case. So the גמרא Gemara says, אסיפא דאידך
בבא קתני. aseifa deidach baba ktani. No, no, no, we're dealing about
with the end, or really the middle of the previous discussion. It's
not contrasting the נדר and the שבועה shvuah to a case like
לא שבועה לא אוכל לך, lo shvuah lo ochal lach, but the
earlier contrast. שבועה shvuah שאיני ישן, שאיני מדבר, שאיני מהלך, okay, אסור.
assur If you say a שבועה shvuah that I won't go, I
won't sleep, I won't talk, whatever, it's forbidden. זה חומר בשבועות מנדרים.
Zeh chomer b'shvuot mib'nedarim. That's stricter from a שבועה shvuah. than a
נדר. Now there, what does it mean? Because there, it's not like
in that case there is no נדר. Remember we said before if
somebody said קרבן שאני הולך, korban she'ani holech, קרבן שאני מדבר, korban
she'ani medaber, that it is binding. Okay? So a נדר works in
that case as well. So if a נדר and a שבועה shvuah
work to make your walking or sitting or talking forbidden, how is
a שבועה shvuah. stricter? Because a שבועה shevuah is biblical in that
case. Somebody takes a שבועה shevuah. I won't go, that's a biblically
binding שבועה. shevuah, Somebody takes a נדר my going is קרבן, korban
is קונם, konam so that... again, the idea of going is an
abstract thing, it's not a physical object, that's only rabbinic. All right?
So he's saying yes, in the most recent משנה, it's not just
a שבועה shevuah. stronger, it's that a שבועה shevuah works and a
נדר doesn't work if you say לא שבועה לא אוכל lo shvuah
lo ochal or something like that as opposed to לא קונם לא
אוכל. lo konam lo ochal. But in the earlier case, both a
שבועה shevuah and a נדר works, but a שבועה shevuah is still
more binding... it's still weightier. שבועה shevuah that I won't go, okay,
is a biblically binding שבועה. shevuah קונם שאני מהלך, Konam she'ani mehalech,
my going is a קרבן, korban, that also is forbidden but not
in as weighty of a way. That's only rabbinic because it's dealing
with not a physical object. All right, yes.
It's more weighty because it's presumably using God's name?
No, I mean, that might be true, but even without using God's
name, it's biblical versus rabbinic. Right? A classic שבועה shevuah that I
won't go, that's a classic biblical שבועה. shevuah You're obligating yourself to
do or not do something. Making my going אסור to me, right,
as a קונם konam like as a forbidden object, if it's not
a physical object, then that's only a rabbinic status that it has,
okay? So the basic difference is biblical versus rabbinic. All right, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. Okay, now we get to this interesting thing about the מצווה.
mitzvah Just one second, I just want to see one thing. Yeah,
I
mean it does mean that they were forcing him, but it means
that he was refusing. היו מסרבין hayu mistarvin is a funny phrase
which means which
means they were they were pushing him and he was refusing. Yeah.
Okay. Pushing him is the. Right.
But it also but it's also his resisting. Okay. Okay, fine. Let's
keep on going. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay.
חומר בנדרים משבועות. chomer mid'nedarim l'shevuos. Now we get the thing about
making מצווה mitzvah objects forbidden on you. רב כהנא מתני, Rav Kahana
masni, רב כהנא Rav Kahana teaches, אמר רב גידל אמר רב, amar
Rav Gidel amar Rav, a statement in the name of רב גידל
Rav Gidel in the name of רב. Rav. ורב טביומי מתני, veRav
Tavyomi masni, אמר רב גידל אמר שמואל. amar Rav Gidel amar Shmuel.
So these are רב גידל Rav Gidel saying in the name of
רב Rav or saying in the name of שמואל. Shmuel. מנין שאין
נשבעין לעבור על המצוות? minayin she-ein nishba'in la'avor al hamitzvos?
How do you know that you can't take a שבועה shevuah
to counteract, to countermand your מצווה mitzvah, obligations? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar,
לא יחל דברו. lo yachel devaro Now again, we've been talking about
לא יחל דברו lo yachel devaro a lot, but that is a
פסוק pasuk that says not only by נדר but also by a
שבועה. shevuah כי ידור נדר להשם או השבע שבועה לאסר אסר על
נפשו לא יחל דברו.
ki yidor neder l'Hashem o hishava shevuah le'esor issar al
nafsho lo yachel devaro. So לא יחל דברו lo yachel devaro. goes
both on כי ידור נדר להשם ki yidor neder l'Hashem and או
השבע שבועה. o hishava shevuah. Okay. So therefore it says in the
case of שבועה, shevua לא יחל דברו. lo yachel devaro דברו לא
יחל אבל מיחלו הוא לחפצי שמים.
devaro lo yachel aval meichalu hu
l'cheftzei Shamayim. So if he is obligating himself about sort of a
his own issues, okay, then it's binding and he can't violate the
שבועה. shevua But if he tries to make a שבועה shevua regarding
חפצי שמים, cheftzei Shamayim, regarding God's words, God's matters, right, so then
that type of a שבועה shevua. is not binding and he can
go ahead and violate it because it was never binding. Okay, so
in his his own sort of, you know, neutral zone, he can
make נדרים, nedarim, he can make a שבועה shevua, and it can
take effect and so on. But if he's trying to do it
in God's zone, it doesn't take effect and he has no prohibitions.
All right. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. You know,
it's interesting to think about other places where the גמרא Gemara sort
of makes those distinctions. Like it says by שבת, Shabbos, right, ממצוא
חפצך ודבר דבר. mimtzo cheftzecha v'daber davar. So it says חפציך אסורים
וחפצי שמים מותרים, cheftzecha asurim v'cheftzei Shamayim mutarim, which is why you
can talk about hiring somebody to like, you know, to teach your
children or something תורה, Torah because even though there's a sense of
like, you know, planning an employment thing, it's ultimately חפצי שמים cheftzei
Shamayim or why the שול shul can make a million announcements about
things that are going to be taking place during the rest of
the week. Okay. But also there's an idea like עוסק במצווה פטור
מן המצווה. osek b'mitzvah patur min hamitzvah. It says, you know, it
says בשבתך בביתך ובלכתך בדרך. beshivtecha b'veitecha uvelachtecha vaderech. בשבתך דידך ובלכתך
דידך. beshivtecha didach uvelachtecha didach. When you're doing your own sitting and
your own standing and your own going around, that's when you're obligated
in מצוות. mitzvos. But when you're already involved in God's matters, when
you're already involved in a מצווה, mitzvah, then you don't become then
you don't become obligated in another מצווה, which is the idea right
of עוסק במצווה פטור מן המצווה. osek b'mitzvah patur min hamitzvah. So
this idea like the תורה's talking about when you're in your sphere,
that's when things things are applying, but when you're operating God's sphere,
as it were, things are different. Okay. So when it's your matters,
then your שבועה shavuah? is binding. When it's God's matters, they are
not. Okay. And how does I get that totally, but how does
it say that in the words? לא יחל, lo yachel, לשון יחלל,
lashon yachalel, החלילו, hachalilu, right? Right, you can violate a שבועה that
was made regarding God's matters. Yeah, you have to add that in.
לא יחל lo yachel when it's your matters. מיחלו, meichalu, you
can no problem, you can violate it because it wasn't binding, right?
Okay. מה ישנא נדר, ma ishna neder, the גמרא Gemara says, but
one minute, that same
לא יחל דברו was
said by a שבועה and by a נדר, right? מה ישנא נדר
ma ishna neder דכתיב איש כי ידור נדר להשם לא יחל דברו?
dechsiv ish ki yidor neder l'Hashem lo yachel devaro? שבועה נמי אכתיב
או השבע שבועה להשם לא יחל דברו. shevuah nami achsiv o hishava
shevuah l'Hashem lo yachel devaro. Now what you might have wanted to
say was the להשם l'Hashem tells you oh no, a נדר can
still work in God's in God's realm because it says it says
כי ידור נדר להשם. ki yidor neder l'Hashem. So a נדר in
God's realm will be binding. But a שבועה also says להשם, l'Hashem,
או השבע שבועה להשם לא יחל דברו. o hishava shevuah l'Hashem lo
yachel devaro. So why by a שבועה do we say if it's
in God's realm it's not binding and by a נדר we say
if it's in God's realm it is binding? Okay, and the פסוק
pasuk is very parallel. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר אביי, amar
Abaye, הא דאמרת הא דאמר הנאת סוכה עלי הא דאמר שבועה שלא
אהנה מן הסוכה. had amart had amar hanat sukka alai had amar
shevuah shelo ehena min hasukka. So אביי Abaye says you're right, it's
really not so explicit in the פסוק. pasuk. There's a logic that
dictates. In one you are basically saying I won't derive benefit from
the סוכה, sukka, so you're not going against God's words, right? You're
not going against whereas if you say a שבועה that I won't
sit in the סוכה, sukka, you are operating in God's realm and
going against God's words. God is telling you to do it and
you're saying you're not going to do it. Okay, as opposed to
the סוכה sukka it's just an it's just a run around, you
know, or it's a not a run around but whatever, it's an
end run and therefore... and therefore you are not directly operating in
God's realm and you are not directly countermanding your obligation and therefore
it takes effect. So now, רבא Rava says he totally buys that
distinction of אביי, Abaye, he just has a problem with the way
אביי Abaye articulated it. אמר רבא וכי מצוות להנות ניתנו? Amar Rava
v'chi mitzvot lehanot nitnu? What do you mean if a guy says
I won't derive benefit from a סוכה, sukkah, he's not allowed to
derive benefit? Okay, doing a מצוה mitzvah is not considered deriving benefit.
Okay, maybe if it's rainy and the סוכה sukkah or sunny and
the סוכה sukkah provides shade he won't be able to do it,
but on a normal day or לולב, lulav, I won't get benefit
from a לולב, lulav, that's even a better example. What type of
benefit do you get from a לולב? lulav? The only benefit you
get is doing a מצוה, mitzvah, that doesn't count as benefit. Now
that's not because מצוות mitzvot are not important, okay, and there's also
רש''י Rashi in a number of places, רש''י Rashi in some places
makes a big theological statement out of it which is like no,
you're supposed to treat these things as עול על צוארם, ol al
tzavaram, as a burden, and therefore it's not a benefit, which is
so funny, it's like against the statement we say very often right
before mourner's קדיש, Kaddish, רבי חנניה בן עקשיא אומר רצה הקדוש ברוך
הוא לזכות את ישראל לפיכך הרבה להם תורה ומצוות. Rabbi Chananya ben
Akashya omer ratza hakadosh baruch hu lezakot et Yisrael lefikach hirba lahem
torah u'mitzvot. We have so many מצוות mitzvot to give us so
many opportunities, right? I mean hopefully that's normally the way we would,
a very positive way about thinking about it. So I don't think
it's not a profound theological statement contra רש''י, Rashi, I don't think
so. I think it's a simple statement that הלכה halacha is this-worldly
and therefore defines issues of benefits in this-worldly terms. So therefore getting
מצוה mitzvah points and doing your religious obligations is not a physical
this-worldly type of a benefit and it's not defined as הנאה. hana'ah.
Give you another example which is this-worldly but because of its lack
of physicality is not a problem. Can you study if you're not
a כהן kohen a cadaver in order to learn medical science, in
order to learn anatomy? You're not supposed to get הנאה hana'ah from
a dead body. So the basic פוסקים poskim say that's not הנאה.
hana'ah. For us it would be what do you mean? It's like
the most hopefully, people of the book, the most powerful הנאה hana'ah
we could have is intellectual expansion, is knowledge. What more הנאה hana'ah
is there than knowledge, right? But nevertheless it's not halachically defined as
gaining knowledge is not halachically defined as it's not physical enough. So
getting מצוות mitzvot and getting knowledge, that's not הנאה. hana'ah. That's what
we live for but maybe but that's not הנאה. hana'ah. Okay, so
that's the idea of מצוות לאו להנות ניתנו. mitzvot lav lehanot nitnu.
It's not a I don't think a broad theological statement of our
attitude towards מצוות, mitzvot, it's more a הלכה halacha statement of how
do you define pleasure in הלכה halacha terms is very much about
a physical this-worldly type of pleasure. Yes. What about you can't study
תורה on תשעה באב? Tisha B'Av? That's because it causes you joy.
That's different, that's interesting, it's different than pleasure and that's different than
okay. It is! It is! Joy is most often not physical. Anyway,
fine. Also many Jewish comedians. Okay, I'm not trying to be oh
anyway, alright, I wasn't trying to okay, yes. Anyway, okay. So רבא
Rava says I get the difference between directly countermanding your biblical obligations
and focusing on an object. However, you cannot say that if you
say I won't get הנאה hana'ah from a לולב lulav it prevents
you from taking a לולב lulav because that's not defined as הנאה.
hana'ah. So the גמרא Gemara says okay, אלא אמר רבא, ela amar
Rava, רבא Rava says here's how you have to articulate it. הא
דאמר ישיבת סוכה עלי hada d'amar yeshivat sukkah alai והא דאמר שבועה
שלא אשב בסוכה. v'hada d'amar shvua shelo eshev basukkah. You don't say
הנאת סוכה עלי, hana'at sukkah alai, I won't get הנאה hana'ah from
the סוכה, sukkah, you say this סוכה sukkah is forbidden to me
regarding sitting in it. So here becomes an important idea which was
somewhat already suggested by the idea like walking is forbidden, my sleeping
is forbidden on me. Can you make something forbidden in ways that
are not about benefiting from it? If the source of נדר is
a קרבן, korban right, a קרבן korban can't derive benefit, can't eat
and so on. As the ר''ן Ran points out you're allowed to
touch a קרבן, korban right, there's no concept of a קרבן korban
being אסור in touching. Could I say קונם konam this book עלי
alai regarding touching? Okay, can you make something forbidden in ways that
is not about it being forbidden in benefit? And that seems to
be what רבא Rava is saying. The סוכה sukkah is forbidden regarding
its use in sitting. Okay, the לולב lulav is forbidden regarding its
use in taking. Okay, which is not a benefit, but it's an
aspect of what it means to deal with this לולב. lulav. And
that seems to be that that actually would be binding. I'll get
let me just finish till the משנה and then I'll talk about
that a little bit more. And it seems like it's binding biblically
because it's preventing you from doing the מצוה. mitzvah. Alright, so that's
a really important expansion of the idea of נדר that it's not
just about הנאה hana'ah or eating, it's about certain actions. And presumably
that's similar to the idea like when you say walking is forbidden
to me, I guess you could have meant the pleasure of walking,
but when before when we said you know my speech, my walking,
etc., right, presumably that also wasn't exactly pleasure-related. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. So now we just to wrap this
up, the גמרא Gemara says like this: ושאין נשבעין לעבור על המצוות
מהכא נפקא? u'she'ein nishba'in la'avor al hamitzvot meihacha na fka? ושאינו נשבע
לבטל את המצוות מהכא נפקא ליה? u-she-eino nishba levatel et ha-mitzvot me-hacha
nafka leih? Do you learn it out from here that you can't
take a שבועה to countermand a מצוה mitzvah obligation? מהתם נפקא ליה.
me-hatam nafka leih. We learn it from over there. דתניא יכול נשבע
לבטל את המצוה ולא ביטל יכול יהא חייב? de-tanya yakhol nishba levatel
et ha-mitzvah ve-lo bittel yakhol yehe hayav? If you took an oath
to negate a מצוה mitzvah and you did not negate the מצוה,
mitzvah, so that way, i.e. you violated your oath, maybe you would
have transgressed your oath? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, the verse says: להרע
או להיטיב, le-hara o le-heitiv, if somebody takes an oath to do
good or to do evil. מה הטבה רשות, mah ha-tava reshut, the
same way when you want to like do something good, meaning not
good but means like positive, it's means something that otherwise you wouldn't
be obligated in, some type of action you're not obligated, אף הרע
af hara when you're sort of prohibiting yourself from something, רשות, reshut,
it means in a matter that's discretionary. יצא נשבע לבטל את המצוה
ולא ביטל yatza nishba levatel et ha-mitzvah ve-lo bittel as opposed to
if you took an oath to negate a מצוה mitzvah and you
did not, שאינה רשות בידו, she-eina reshut beyado, that's not discretionary, so
your שבועה isn't binding. Okay, so therefore if you took a שבועה
to not sit in a סוכה sukkah and you sat in a
סוכה, sukkah, you did not violate your שבועה. So why do you
need two פסוקים, psukim, one based on להרע או להיטיב le-hara o
le-heitiv and the other is יחל דברו? So the גמרא says: חד
קרא למיפטרי מקרבן שבועה וחד למיפטרי מלאו דשבועה. chad kra le-miftrei mi-korban
shevua ve-chad le-miftrei mi-lav de-shevua. There are two things it's exempting you
from, one is if you do it willingly, you know, you willingly
violate, you don't get lashes, you don't violate the לאו, lav, and
the other is that you don't ever have to bring a קרבן
for it, okay, and maybe there would have been a different standard,
maybe it would have been binding vis-a-vis the קרבן but not binding
vis-a-vis the לאו. lav. So these two פסוקים psukim tell you it's
binding in no way. By the way though, the ר"ן Ran underscores
that that doesn't mean you're not going to get lashes. You got
lashes for שבועת שוא. shevuat shav. You got lashes as soon as
you took the שבועה, but after you took it, it doesn't remain
binding on you because it was coming to negate a מצוה. mitzvah.
So the problem was it was a, you know, it was an
oath in vain, but it's not a binding oath that's now is
going to impact you. Now I want to say one or two
things about these important issues about like a נדר of מצוה. mitzvah.
First, if you take a look at the ר"ן Ran here, a
couple of very important things. First, this issue that you can focus
on actions and not הנאה. hana'ah. So if the ר"ן Ran, says
three lines from the bottom, the ר"ן Ran says like this, he
says, or four lines from the bottom towards the end, yeah, on
the עמוד ב, four lines from the bottom, like last third of
the line, he says: ולפי זה אמר, u-le-fi zeh omar, if somebody
said: קונם זריקת צור לים עליו אסור, konam zerikat tzor le-yam alav
assur, that this rock, this pebble is קונם konam, on me regarding
throwing it in the ocean. Right, he's just trying to give an
example that it has nothing to do with הנאה, hana'ah, okay, although
I don't know, maybe you enjoy skipping rocks. Anyway, אף על פי
שאין לו בזריקה זו הנאה אסור לזרקו, af al pi she-ein lo
bi-zerikah zo hana'ah assur le-zorko, okay, because now we have identified that
there you can make something forbidden vis-a-vis an action not vis-a-vis הנאה.
hana'ah. מיהו דוקא במפורש ישיבת סוכה זריקת צור. mihu davka bi-meforesh yeshivat
sukkah zerikat tzor. You have to be very explicit if you want
to only if you want to forbid it in that way. אבל
באומר קונם סוכה עלי קונם צור עלי, aval be-omar konam sukkah alai
konam tzor alai, but if you just generically said it's a קונם,
konam then יושב ישיבה של מצוה וזורקה אותה צור. yoshev yeshiva she-mitzvah
ve-zorikah otah tzor. If you just said קונם konam this rock is
forbidden to me, you could still throw it into the ocean, you
can't get הנאה, hana'ah, okay, the default of the word קונם konam,
is things that are defined as הנאה. hana'ah. All right, so therefore
you can make it mean something other than הנאה, hana'ah, you could
make it that I can get הנאה hana'ah from this rock but
I can't throw it in the ocean, okay, if you said that,
you can make that work. But if you just said a straight
out קונם, it would be אסור בהנאה assur be-hana'ah and מותר muttar
to throw into the ocean. All right, so that's an interesting idea
that a קרבן can work relating to using it in certain ways,
not just הנאה. hana'ah. Point number one. Point number two, just an
important concept relating to the idea of מצות לאו ליהנות ניתנו, mitzvot
lav le-henot nitnu, that is let me just find here the ר"ן
Ran I wanted to read, I want to do one line from
the ר"ן, one line from תוספות. Tosafot. Okay, no, no, so first
so here's the question, question number two. One is that you can
relate to a certain action, this סוכה sukkah regarding its sitting. But
here's the other point, why is this a physical action, right, in
the משנה, you okay there Bobby? Yeah. In the example of רבא,
Rava, you said ישיבת סוכה עלי, yeshivat sukkah alai, which is again
this abstract idea, the sitting in a סוכה sukkah is forbidden to
me. That's a דבר שאין בו ממש. davar she-ein bo mamash. That
should only be binding דרבנן. de-rabbanan. And if this is getting in
the way of you doing a מצוה דאורייתא, mitzvah de-oraita, the מצוה
דאורייתא mitzvah de-oraita should override. So how would, if you really wanted
it binding דאורייתא, de-oraita, you should have said קונם סוכה עלי לישיבתה,
konam sukkah alai le-yeshivatah, that you're forbidding the object of the סוכה
sukkah regarding its sitting as opposed to saying קונם ישיבת סוכה עלי,
konam yeshivat sukkah alai, the sitting is forbidden to me. So let's
take a look at the ר"ן dealing with this question. The ר"ן
says, two lines before the lines get wide: ואם תאמר דכי אמר
ישיבת סוכה עלי מאי הוי, ve-im tomar de-ki amar yeshivat sukkah alai
mai havi, who cares if you say the sitting is forbidden to
me? הדבר שאין בו ממש הוא. ha davar she-ein bo mamash hu.
That's not a physical object. יש לומר. yesh lomar. הכא במאי עסקינן
כגון דאמר קונם סוכה לישיבתה עלי. hacha bemai askinan kigon de'amar konom
sukkah liyeshivasa alai. Yeah, that is what you said. You said the
sukkah is forbidden regarding its sukkah sitting. ורבא לא חש ליה לתרתי
לישנא הנד אמר אביי, verava lo chashlei tartei lishna hanad amar Abaye,
ואי נמי, ve'ei nami, it's, you're right, דבאומר סוכה לישיבתה עסקינן debeomer
sukkah liyeshivasa askinan that you have to say the sukkah is forbidden
for its sitting. Okay, but if you said the sitting is forbidden,
that would only be דרבנן. derabbanan. And now, אבל בתוספות אמרו, aval
betosfos amru, here's a different other opinion. תוספות tosfos said שאפילו אמר
קונם ישיבת סוכה עלי, she'afilu amar konom yeshivath sukkah alai, even if
you just said the sitting is forbidden, מהני, mahani, it works. דלא
מקרי דבר שאין בו ממש, delo mikrei davar she'ein bo mamash, and
that's not like you're dealing with something that is a non-physical thing.
אלא בשאינו מזכיר שם החפץ שאוסר עליו, ela beshe'eino mazkir shem hachefetz
she'oser alav, only if you never mention any object, כגון שאני ישן,
kigon she'ani yashen, my sleeping is forbidden, my speaking is forbidden, שאני
מדבר. אבל כשמזכיר החפץ הנאסר, aval kshemazkir hachefetz hane'esar, when in passing,
even in passing, you mention an object, דבר שיש בו ממש הוא.
davar sheyesh bo mamash hu. So if you say the sitting of
the sukkah is forbidden on me, since you said the word סוכה,
sukkah, although you were referring to the act of sitting, that's considered
enough to be a biblically binding נדר. Okay, so a little bizarre
idea. If to say that, I would have said more because of
an idea of a יד. yad. That if you say the sitting
of a sukkah, we're going to interpret that to mean the sukkah
is forbidden for its sitting. Okay, but again there are like two
חידושים chidushim here. One is it's a very important idea of רבא.
Rava. Because you can't say הנאת סוכה עלי hana'ath sukkah alai and
you have to say ישיבת סוכה עלי. yeshivath sukkah alai. Number one
is we're introducing an idea that you can make an איסור נדר
issur neder on an object that prevents, prohibits things that are not
הנאה, hana'ah, that are prohibited certain types of uses that are not
הנאה. hana'ah. Number one. Number two, the simple sense of רבא Rava
is you focus on the action not the object, okay. And therefore
that gets us back to this question about דבר שאין בו ממש.
davar she'ein bo mamash. Either we're going to maybe reinterpret it that
way, or we're saying that רבא Rava actually meant that you did
say it that way, but nevertheless that's another important aspect of רבא's
Rava statement. We have one more minute, I just want to, I
just want to read one important other point here. Does his statement
apply to שבועה? No, נדר. All נדר? Yeah, right. One minute. Okay,
no, this is a point of תוספות tosfos that I don't want
to belabor. All right, we'll end here for now. Okay. All right,
yes, that's the point.